I'd like to start, if I may,
أحب أن أبدأ، لو سمحتم لي،
with the story of the Paisley snail.
بقصة الحلزون بيزلي.
On the evening of the 26th of August, 1928,
في مساء 26 من أغسطس، 1928،
May Donoghue took a train from Glasgow
استقلت ماي دونغو القطار، من غلاسكو،
to the town of Paisley, seven miles east of the city,
إلى بلدة بيزلي، التي تبعد سبعة أميال شرق المدينة،
she had a Scots ice cream float,
أخذت كأس مثلجات "سكوتس"،
a mix of ice cream and ginger beer
وهي مزيج من المثلجات وجعة الزنجبيل
bought for her by a friend.
ابتاعها لها صديق لها.
The ginger beer came in a brown, opaque bottle
قُدِّمت لها جعة الزنجبيل في قارورة بنية شفافة
labeled "D. Stevenson, Glen Lane, Paisley."
تحمل علامة "د. ستيفنسون.غلين لين، بيزلي".
She drank some of the ice cream float,
احتست بعضا من المثلجات،
but as the remaining ginger beer was poured
لكن بينما كانت تسكب ما تبقى من جعة الزنجبيل
into her tumbler,
في قدحها،
a decomposed snail
طفى حلزون متحلل
floated to the surface of her glass.
إلى سطح كأسها.
Three days later, she was admitted
بعد ثلاثة أيام، تم إدخالها
to the Glasgow Royal Infirmary
إلى المستشفى الملكي في غلاسكو،
and diagnosed with severe gastroenteritis
وتم تشخيص حالتها على أنها التهاب في المعدة والأمعاء
and shock.
مع وجود صدمة.
The case of Donoghue vs. Stevenson that followed
قضية دونغو ضد ستيفنسون التي تلت
set a very important legal precedent:
شكلت سابقة قضائية مهمة:
Stevenson, the manufacturer of the ginger beer,
ستيفنسون، مُصَنِّع جعة الزنجبيل،
was held to have a clear duty of care
حُكم عليه بوجود واجب الرعاية بشكل واضح
towards May Donoghue,
اتجاه" ماي دونغهو".
even though there was no contract between them,
حتى إن لم يكن بينهما أي عقد مبرم،
and, indeed, she hadn't even bought the drink.
حيث أنها لم تكن من اشترى الشراب حتى.
One of the judges, Lord Atkin, described it like this:
أحد القضاة، لورد أتكين، وصف هذه الحالة كالتالي:
You must take care to avoid acts or omissions
عليك أن تتوخى الحذر لتتفادى أفعالا أو حالات سهو
which you can reasonably foresee
التي من الممكن أن تتوقع بشكل معقول
would be likely to injure your neighbor.
أنها ستؤذي جارك.
Indeed, one wonders that without a duty of care,
وبالفعل، يتساءل المرء أنه من غير واجب الرعاية،
how many people would have had to suffer
كم عدد الناس الذين من الممكن أن يكونوا قد عانوا
from gastroenteritis before Stevenson eventually went out of business.
من التهاب المعدة والأمعاء قبل أن يخلى سبيل "ستفنسون".
Now please hang on to that Paisley snail story,
أرجوكم أن تعيروا اهتمامكم إلى قصة حلزون بيزلي،
Last year, the Hansard Society, a nonpartisan charity
في السنة الماضية، قامت جمعية "مجتمع هانسارد" الخيرية غير الحزبية
which seeks to strengthen parliamentary democracy
والتي تسعى إلى تعزيز الديمقراطية البرلمانية
and encourage greater public involvement in politics
وتشجع على المشاركة السياسية بشكل أكبر
published, alongside their annual audit
بنشر، بالموازاة مع تقريرهم السنوي
of political engagement, an additional section
عن المشاركة السياسية، جزء إضافيا
devoted entirely to politics and the media.
مخصصا بشكل كامل للسياسة والإعلام.
Here are a couple of rather depressing observations
إليكم بعضا من الملاحظات المحبطة
from that survey.
من هذه الدراسة.
Tabloid newspapers do not appear
لا تبدو الصحف الشعبية مشجعة
to advance the political citizenship of their readers,
على زيادة المواطنة السياسية لقرائها،
relative even to those
بالمقارنة مع أولئك الذين
who read no newspapers whatsoever.
لا يقرؤون أية جرائد على الإطلاق.
Tabloid-only readers are twice as likely to agree
قراء الجرائد الشعبية فقط هم أكثر عرضة بالضعف للاتفاق
with a negative view of politics
مع آراء سياسية سلبية
than readers of no newspapers.
بالمقارنة مع أولئك الذين لا يقرؤون أية جرائد.
They're not just less politically engaged.
هم ليسوا فقط أقل انخراطا في المجال السياسي.
They are consuming media that reinforces
هم يستهلكون إعلاما يقوي
their negative evaluation of politics,
تقييمهم السلبي للتحول السياسي،
thereby contributing to a fatalistic and cynical
وبالتالي يساهمون في تكوين
attitude to democracy and their own role within it.
موقف استسلامي اتجاه الديمقراطية ودورهم فيها.
Little wonder that the report concluded that
لم يكن غريبا أن ينتهي التقرير إلى أنه
in this respect, the press, particularly the tabloids,
في هذا الصدد، الصحافة، وبالأخص الجرائد الشعبية،
appear not to be living up to the importance
لا ترتقي إلى الدور المهم
of their role in our democracy.
الذي تلعبه في الديمقراطية.
Now I doubt if anyone in this room would seriously
أشك الآن إن كان هناك أي أحد في هذه القاعة
challenge that view.
قد يعترض جديا على هذا الرأي.
But if Hansard are right, and they usually are,
لكن إن كان رأي "هاسفارد" صحيحا، وهو في الغالب كذلك،
then we've got a very serious problem on our hands,
فهذا يعني أن لدينا مشكلا جديا بين أيدينا،
and it's one that I'd like to spend the next 10 minutes
وهو ما أريد أن أتحدث عنه في الدقائق العشر القادمة
focusing upon.
وأن أركز عليه.
Since the Paisley snail,
منذ حادثة حلزون بيزلي،
and especially over the past decade or so,
وخصوصا في العقد الأخير أو نحو ذلك،
a great deal of thinking has been developed
حصل تطور كبير جدا في طريقة التفكير
around the notion of a duty of care
حول مفهوم واجب الرعاية
as it relates to a number of aspects of civil society.
نظرا لعلاقته بمجموعة من جوانب المجتمع المدني.
Generally a duty of care arises when one individual
غالبا ما يظهر واجب الرعاية حين يقوم
or a group of individuals undertakes an activity
فرد أو مجموعة من الأشخاص بنشاط
which has the potential to cause harm to another,
من المحتمل أن يجلب الأذى للآخر،
either physically, mentally or economically.
سوا ء جسديا أو ذهنيا أو اقتصاديا.
This is principally focused on obvious areas,
وهذا يركز بالأساس على نواح بديهية،
such as our empathetic response to children and young people,
كتجاوبنا العاطفي مع الأطفال والشباب،
to our service personnel, and to the elderly and infirm.
مع موظفي الخدمات وكبار السن والعجزة.
It is seldom, if ever, extended to equally important arguments
ونادرا ما، إن لم يكن مستحيلا، ما يتسع هذا ليتضمن حججا مهمة
around the fragility of our present system of government,
حول هشاشة النظام الحكومي الحالي،
to the notion that honesty, accuracy and impartiality
ليشمل المفهوم الذي يعتبر فيه الصدق والدقة والنزاهة
are fundamental to the process of building
ركائز أساسية لبناء
and embedding an informed,
وترسيخ ديمقراطية
participatory democracy.
واعية وتشاركية.
And the more you think about it,
وكلما فكرتم في الأمر أكثر،
the stranger that is.
كلما بدا أكثر غرابة.
A couple of years ago, I had the pleasure
قبل بضع سنوات، كان لي شرف
of opening a brand new school
افتتاح مدرسة جديدة
in the northeast of England.
في الشمال الشرقي لإيرلندا.
It had been renamed by its pupils as Academy 360.
سُمِّيَت من طرف تلاميذها باسم "أكاديمية 360".
As I walked through their impressive,
وقد تجولت في القاعة الأساسية لمدرستهم
glass-covered atrium,
المثيرة للإعجاب، المغطاة بالزجاج
in front of me, emblazoned on the wall
وأمامي، وقد كُتِبَت على الحائط بشكل مزركش
in letters of fire
وبحروف من نار
was Marcus Aurelius's famous injunction:
وصية ماركوس أوريلوس الشهيرة :
If it's not true, don't say it;
إن لم يكن ما ستقوله صحيحا، لا تقله،
if it's not right, don't do it.
إن لم يكن ما ستفعله صوابا، لا تفعله.
The head teacher saw me staring at it,
رآني رئيس الأساتذة أمعن النظر فيها،
and he said, "Oh, that's our school motto."
فقال : "أوه هذا شعار مدرستنا".
On the train back to London,
وفي طريق عودتي بالقطار إلى لندن،
I couldn't get it out of my mind.
لم تكن تلك العبارة لتفارق تفكيري.
I kept thinking, can it really have taken us
فظلت أفكر وأفكر، هل تطلب فعلا من الأمر
over 2,000 years to come to terms
2000 سنة لنصل إلى معنى
with that simple notion
هذا المفهوم البسيط
as being our minimum expectation of each other?
على أنه أقل ما يمكننا أن نتوقعه من بعضنا البعض؟
Isn't it time that we develop this concept
ألم يحن الوقت لنطور مفهوم
of a duty of care
واجب الرعاية
and extended it to include a care
ونوسعه ليشمل الاهتمام
for our shared but increasingly endangered democratic values?
بقيمنا الديمقراطية المشتركة والمهددة بالخطر بشكل متزايد؟
After all, the absence of a duty of care
في جميع الأحوال، غياب واجب الرعاية
within many professions
في العديد من المهن
can all too easily amount to accusations of negligence,
يمكن أن يوصلنا بشكل سهل جدا إلى اتهامنا بالإهمال،
and that being the case, can we be really comfortable with the thought
ومع وصولنا إلى هذه الحال، هل سيكون من المريح وجود فكرة
that we're in effect being negligent
أننا بالفعل مقصرون تجاه
in respect of the health of our own societies
الصحة العامة لمجتمعاتنا
and the values that necessarily underpin them?
والقيم الراسخة فيها؟
Could anyone honestly suggest, on the evidence,
هل يمكن لأي أحد أن يقترح بصراحة، مع تقديم البراهين،
that the same media which Hansard so roundly condemned
أن الإعلام ذاته، الذي اتهمته بشكل غير مباشر جمعية "هانسارد"
have taken sufficient care to avoid behaving
قد اتخذ الاحتياطات الكافية ليتجنب التعامل
in ways which they could reasonably have foreseen
بطريقة كان بإمكانهم أن يتوقعوا بشكل معقول
would be likely to undermine or even damage
أنه من الممكن أن تضعف أو تلحق الضرر
our inherently fragile democratic settlement.
بنظامنا الديمقراطي الهش بالأساس.
Now there will be those who will argue
هناك من سيجادل الآن بالقول
that this could all too easily drift into a form
أن هذا سيجرنا بسهولة إلى نوع
of censorship, albeit self-censorship,
من الرقابة، وإن كانت رقابة ذاتية،
but I don't buy that argument.
لكنني لن أستمع لهذا الجدال،
It has to be possible
يجب أن يكون من الممكن
to balance freedom of expression
الموازنة بين حرية التعبير
with wider moral and social responsibilities.
والمسؤوليات الأخلاقية والاجتماعية الأوسع.
Let me explain why by taking the example
دعوني أشرح لكم السبب من خلال مثال
from my own career as a filmmaker.
أقتبسه من تجربتي المهنية كمخرج سينمائي.
Throughout that career, I never accepted
خلال مسيرتي المهنية تلك، لم أتقبل قط
that a filmmaker should set about putting
أن يضع مخرج ما
their own work outside or above what he or she
عمله الخاص خارج أو فوق ما يعتقد
believed to be a decent set of values
أو تعتقد أنها قيم محترمة
for their own life, their own family,
بالنسبة لحياتهم الخاصة،أو لعائلاتهم
and the future of the society in which we all live.
أو مستقبل المجتمع الذي نعيش فيه جميعا.
I'd go further.
سأذهب لأبعد من هذا.
A responsible filmmaker should never devalue their work
لا يجب على أي مخرج محترم أن يحط من قيمة عمله
to a point at which it becomes less than true
لدرجة يصبح فيها أقل واقعية
to the world they themselves wish to inhabit.
بالنسبة للعالم الذي هم بأنفسهم يتمنون العيش فيه.
As I see it, filmmakers, journalists, even bloggers
كما يبدو لي، المخرجون والصحفيون وحتى المدونون
are all required to face up to the social expectations
كلهم مدعوون إلى مواجهة التوقعات الاجتماعية
that come with combining the intrinsic power of their medium
من خلال دمج القوة المحورية لوسائطهم
with their well-honed professional skills.
مع مهاراتهم المهنية المتَّقذة.
Obviously this is not a mandated duty,
بطبيعة الحال، ليس هذا تكليفا واجبا،
but for the gifted filmmaker and the responsible journalist
لكن بالنسبة لمخرج موهوب وصحفي محترم
or even blogger, it strikes me as being utterly inescapable.
أوحتى مدوَّن، فيبدو لي أنه أمر لا مفر منه على الإطلاق.
We should always remember that our notion
علينا دائما أن نتذكر أن مفهومنا
of individual freedom and its partner, creative freedom,
للحرية الفردية، وشريكتها، الحرية الإبداعية،
is comparatively new
هو جديد نسبيا
in the history of Western ideas,
في تاريخ الأفكار الغربية،
and for that reason, it's often undervalued
ولهذا السبب، فغالبا ما تُبخَس قيمتها
and can be very quickly undermined.
وبسرعة يمكن إضعاف قوتها.
It's a prize easily lost,
إنها كنز يمكن فقده بسرعة،
and once lost, once surrendered,
فإن ضاع، أو تم التنازل عنه،
it can prove very, very hard to reclaim.
سيكون من الصعب للغاية استعادته.
And its first line of defense
يجب أن يكون خط دفاعنا الأول
has to be our own standards,
هو قيمنا ومعاييرنا نحن،
not those enforced on us by a censor or legislation,
وليست تلك التي فُرِضت علينا من طرف الرقابة أو التشريعات،
our own standards and our own integrity.
معاييرنا ونزاهتنا نحن.
Our integrity as we deal with those
نزاهتنا التي نتحلى بها حين نتعامل
with whom we work
مع زملائنا
and our own standards as we operate within society.
ومعاييرنا التي نتعامل بها داخل المجتمع.
And these standards of ours
وهذه المعايير الخاصة بنا
need to be all of a piece with a sustainable social agenda.
عليها أن تكون جزءا من المخطط الاجتماعي المستدام.
They're part of a collective responsibility,
فهي تشكل جزءا من المسؤولية الجماعية،
the responsibility of the artist or the journalist
مسؤولية الفنان أو الصحفي
to deal with the world as it really is,
أن يتعامل مع العالم كما هو،
and this, in turn, must go hand in hand
وعلى هذا،في المقابل، أن يتماشى يدا بيد
with the responsibility of those governing society
مع مسؤولية أولئك الذين يسيِّرون المجتمع
to also face up to that world,
لكي يواجهوا ذلك العالم،
and not to be tempted to misappropriate
ولا يغتروا بتقييم أسباب
the causes of its ills.
أمراضه بشكل خاطئ.
Yet, as has become strikingly clear
إلا أنه، كما أصبح يبدو واضحا بشكل ملفت
over the last couple of years,
خلال السنوات القليلة الماضية،
such responsibility has to a very great extent
كيف تم إلغاء هذه المسؤولية بشكل كيبر جدا
been abrogated by large sections of the media.
من طرف قطاع عريض من وسائل الإعلام.
And as a consequence, across the Western world,
وكنيتجة لهذا، في العالم الغربي كله،
the over-simplistic policies of the parties of protest
تشكل السياسات التبسيطية التي يطرحها أطراف النزاع
and their appeal to a largely disillusioned,
وجاذبيتها الكبيرة لطبقة المحبَطين،
older demographic,
من كبار السن،
along with the apathy and obsession with the trivial
إلى جانب اللامبالاة والهوس بالتفاهة
that typifies at least some of the young,
التي تطبع على الأقل بعضا من الشباب،
taken together, these and other similarly
كل هذه الأمورمعا، وأخرى مشابهة
contemporary aberrations
من الانحرافات المعاصرة
are threatening to squeeze the life
تهدد بمحو الحياة
out of active, informed debate and engagement,
من أي مشاركة أو حوار فعّال وواع،
and I stress active.
وهنا أركز على كلمة "فعّال".
The most ardent of libertarians might argue
قد يجادل أكبر مناصري الحرية،
that Donoghue v. Stevenson should have been thrown out of court
أن قضية دونغهو وستفنسون كان لا بد أن تغادر أروقة المحاكم،
and that Stevenson would eventually have gone out of business
وأن ستفنسون كان ليخرج في نهاية المطاف من عالم الأعمال،
if he'd continued to sell ginger beer with snails in it.
إن استمر في بيع جعة الزنجبيل مع وجود حلزونات بها.
But most of us, I think, accept some small role
لكن غالبيتنا،كما أعتقد، يتفق مع فكرة وجود دور صغير
for the state to enforce a duty of care,
للدولة في تعزيز مفهوم واجب الرعاية،
and the key word here is reasonable.
والكلمة الأساسية لوصف هذا الدور هي "معقول".
Judges must ask, did they take reasonable care
على القضاة أن يسألوا : هل أعاروا الأمر اهتماما معقولا
and could they have reasonably foreseen
وهل كان بإمكانهم أن يتوقعوا بشكل معقول
the consequences of their actions?
نتائج قراراتهم؟
Far from signifying overbearing state power,
بعيدا عن معنى تجاوز سلطة الدولة،
it's that small common sense test of reasonableness
لكن ذلك الاختبار للفكر السليم للعقلانية:
that I'd like us to apply to those in the media
هذا ما أود أن نطبقه على من يعملون في الإعلام
who, after all, set the tone and the content
الذين، في جميع الأحوال، يضعون النبرة والمحتوى
for much of our democratic discourse.
في معظم أحاديثنا الديمقراطية.
Democracy, in order to work, requires that
الديمقراطية، لكي تعمل، تحتاج
reasonable men and women take the time to understand and debate
إلى رجال ونساء عقلانيين يأخذون وقتهم لكي يفهموا ويناقشوا
difficult, sometimes complex issues,
مواضيع صعبة، وفي بعض الأحيان معقدة،
and they do so in an atmosphere which strives
ويقومون بهذا في جو يناضل
for the type of understanding that leads to,
من أجل هذا النوع من الفهم الذي يؤدي،
if not agreement, then at least a productive
إن لم يكن للاتفاق، فعلى الأقل
and workable compromise.
إلى توافق بناء وعملي.
Politics is about choices,
السياسة عبارة عن اختيارات،
and within those choices, politics is about priorities.
وضمن هذه الاختيارات، فالسياسة عبارة عن أولويات.
It's about reconciling conflicting preferences
يتعلق الأمر بمصالحة الأفضليات المتناقضة،
wherever and whenever possibly based on fact.
أينما ووقتما وجدت مبنية على أساس واقعي.
But if the facts themselves are distorted,
ولكن إن كانت الوقائع نفسها مشوهة،
the resolutions are likely only to create further conflict,
فإن من المرجح ألا تخلق القرارات سوى صراع أعمق،
with all the stresses and strains on society
مع كل تلك الضغوط والتوترات الاجتماعية
that inevitably follow.
التي ستتلوها لا محالة.
The media have to decide:
على الإعلام أن يقرر:
Do they see their role as being to inflame
هل يرى الإعلاميون دورهم في تأجيج الناس
or to inform?
أم في إخبارهم؟
Because in the end, it comes down to a combination
لأن الأمر في نهاية المطاف، هو مزيج
of trust and leadership.
من الثقة والريادة.
Fifty years ago this week, President John F. Kennedy
يصادف هذا الأسبوع الذكرى الخمسين، لإلقاء الرئيس جون.ف. كينيدي
made two epoch-making speeches,
لخطابين تاريخيين،
the first on disarmament and the second on civil rights.
الأول عن نزع السلاح، والثاني عن الحقوق المدنية
The first led almost immediately
أدى الأول بشكل فوري
to the Nuclear Test Ban Treaty,
إلى توقيع معاهدة حظر التجارب النووية،
and the second led to the 1964 Civil Rights Act,
والثاني إلى إنشاء قانون الحقوق المدنية لسنة 1964،
both of which represented giant leaps forward.
واللذان شكلا معا قفزتين نوعيتين نحو الأمام.
Democracy, well-led and well-informed,
الديمقراطية، المسيرة بشكل جيد، والواعية بشكل جيد،
can achieve very great things,
يمكن أن تصل إلى نتائج عظيمة،
We have to trust that those making those decisions
علينا أن نثق أن من يصنعون تلك القرارات،
are acting in the best interest not of themselves
يعملون من أجل تحقيق أفضل المصالح، ليس لأنفسهم
but of the whole of the people.
بل لجميع الناس.
We need factually-based options,
نحتاج إلى خيارات قائمة على الوقائع،
clearly laid out,
موضوعة بوضوح،
not those of a few powerful
وليس إلى تلك الشركات القليلة
and potentially manipulative corporations
التي من المحتمل أن تكون متلاعبة
pursuing their own frequently narrow agendas,
والتي تسعى باستمرار وراء مخططاتها الضيقة،
but accurate, unprejudiced information
بل نحتاج إلى معلومة دقيقة، غير متحيزة
with which to make our own judgments.
يمكن أن نصنع من خلالها رأينا الخاص.
If we want to provide decent, fulfilling lives
إذا أردنا أن نوفر حياة محترمة ومرضية
for our children and our children's children,
لأولادنا وأحفادنا،
we need to exercise to the very greatest degree possible
علينا أن نتمرن إلى أقصى حد ممكن
that duty of care for a vibrant,
على واجب الرعاية ذاك، من أجل
and hopefully a lasting, democracy.
ديمقراطية حيوية ومستدامة
Thank you very much for listening to me.
شكرا جزيلا على إنصاتكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)